<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.2.2">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2023-02-12T16:05:21-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Christopher Michael Rytting</title><subtitle>This is my new website</subtitle><entry><title type="html">On Cost</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2022/08/25/on-cost/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="On Cost" /><published>2022-08-25T00:00:00-06:00</published><updated>2022-08-25T00:00:00-06:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2022/08/25/on-cost</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2022/08/25/on-cost/"><![CDATA[<p>One time I heard Ezra Klein talk about how someone needed to invent a technology that made some activity much easier. It’s probably annoying to read that sentence and not to have filled in after just what the activity was, but I think the ideas here will apply generally.</p>

<p>Let’s just imagine that what he wanted to happen was increased generosity. He’s normatively saying that more generosity should happen, and that the obstacle to it happening is the barrier to it happening, the cost faced by people trying to do it, and that if you made it cheaper, more people would do it. That’s an economics-ey way to frame the decision by people to do a thing or not to do the thing, as if what mattered more weren’t taste or attention or something more subjective or irrational.</p>

<p>In general, can you frame things this way, of thinking of people’s decisions to either do the thing or not as a function of cost, first and foremost?</p>

<p>Well, you might be thinking, something can be a function of cost and not depend exclusively on it. You could even have something be a function of cost and not depend <em>mainly</em> on it. What matters with evaluating interventions is if they will make <em>a</em> difference, not the biggest difference.</p>

<p>To which I’d say, sure, you can make something cheaper and someone will start doing it for whom it was too expensive before. But consider how many people are, in effect, watching prices and actively deciding whether or not to do something, how many people have, in effect, the “price tracker” turned on and alerting them. Mightn’t it be the case that these prospective consumers are either actively or passively ignoring prices or that they get distracted from making a purchase, rather than them actively deciding “these prices… TOO HIGH FOR NOW!”</p>

<p>The reason I’m going on and on at length about this is that this metaphor of making a technology for solving a social problem that people could choose to solve now but don’t really resonated with me. It rings true that if you build it, they will come. I think of doing machine learning and a big impediment to my doing it over the course of my career has honestly been that I felt stupid in conversations with people about it, and if it had been easier to understand, I wouldn’t have faced the cost of feeling embarrassed and I could have been a productive member of those conversations. I think of waking up and running harder or more consistently than I have over the years, and if that had been easier, then I would have done more of it. So when someone proposes that thing X doesn’t happen enough and we need to make a technology that makes it easier, I see that as a call to arms, to build the technology and thereby bring about more of the thing in the world.</p>

<p>I get excited about building out things to make research easier, tech to make productive conversations easier, tech to make eating healthy and exercising easier (can you tell the things I struggle with in my own life yet?), and I start evaluated the goodness or the badness of my ideas by the yardstick of whether it is a technology that makes some activity easier.</p>

<p>But then I start wondering what we even mean by costs, and whether costs mean giving something up, paying a price of some kind out of a vat of resources that you positively possess, or whether they are supposed to be just a generalized symbol for what gets in our way in “making purchases”, which itself stands in as a generalized symbol for doing behaviors.</p>

<p>When terms get this general, what stands in our way of doing something, the something we might do, it starts to feel like a tautology to say we “face high costs” for doing something because, well, yeah, if it weren’t for all the reasons I were doing something, I suppose I could probably be doing that thing!</p>

<p>At some base level, this feels like a dumb conversation since we’re talking about prices and purchases and whether these things are really informing consumer choice, but isn’t it true that the realest thing is whether someone has food to eat, whether they have a roof over their heads, whether their family is safe? This whole blog post can be read as a skepticism that anything can be considered true about whether incentives matter; but I don’t really question whether incentives matter. I think the reason social media is so consumed-upon-an-endeavor is the <em>ease</em> of it and the <em>pleasantry</em> of it, i.e., it’s cheap and it’s nice. That’s not really true about anything else to the same extent that social media is. You only have to press a button, ultimate ease, and exert no further effort and you bring the entertainers into your home. If it were easier to have a spiritual experience during prayer, or if it were easier to get into a book, to the point that you actually felt enlivened by its ideas, or if it were easier to feel pleasure instead of pain by sitting there and meditating, then I think no one would get on social media.</p>

<p>Which brings me to another last irrationality which feels <em>so worth</em> reflecting on: If I get on social media and get a unit of pleasure for zero effort, I basically am gonna be trigger-giddy at my free unit. A no-brainer! But if you had to compare one unit of pleasure for zero effort to 10 units of pleasure for 5 units of effort, I think you’d have a more rewarding experience because I think we care a lot more about the net than we do about the ratio. I also think we care about opportunity cost, and I’m aware, after pulling the lever for my one unit pleasure, what I could have done with the half an hour on instagram, even if it technically was free. Capitalism, maybe, has tuned us to think of costs in terms of price, which is variable, and which can determine our purchasing behavior, and ignore what we else we could do with the money or what we could do with the money in five weeks if we don’t spend it now. Maybe this is so because everything is talked about in terms of price, instead of what it costs.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[One time I heard Ezra Klein talk about how someone needed to invent a technology that made some activity much easier. It’s probably annoying to read that sentence and not to have filled in after just what the activity was, but I think the ideas here will apply generally.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">What Do Mavericks Need to Understand?</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2022/08/24/mavericks/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="What Do Mavericks Need to Understand?" /><published>2022-08-24T00:00:00-06:00</published><updated>2022-08-24T00:00:00-06:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2022/08/24/mavericks</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2022/08/24/mavericks/"><![CDATA[<p>Partly motivated by my writing last night, where I take an interest in how maverick thinkers can actually buck against conventional wisdoms too unwieldy for a single person to have been responsible for them, I’m here tonight to meditate on how humans organize to do things that are too complicated for any individual human to do, such as the generation of a conventional wisdom.</p>

<p>One adage that does full dramatic justice to how little any of us know: No single person knows how to make a pencil–with all its requisite synthesis, harvest, and refinining of graphite, wood, paint, metal, and rubber. This, of course, is not even to speak of *<em>insert your imagination going wild</em>*.</p>

<h3 id="industry">Industry</h3>

<p>So with respect to industry, I can make sense of this in theory, that someone’s responsibility is to decide “We at Firm X, we build cars, got it, Firm X?” and someone else’s responsbility is to say “Yeah, I’ll build the wheels. Amy, Doug, and Whitney, you come with me.” and someone else’s responsibility to say “Yeah, I’ll build the seats. Luis, Peng, and Nadia come with me”. Then once they get into their little corners of the factory. It might fall to Amy to procure the rubber and it might fall to Peng to get the foam, etc. etc. on down the line until all the people at the end nodes of the tree have their work done and pass their work back up the line where they hand the CEO, the person who decided they would build cars, the built car.</p>

<p>I can see it taking literally a lifetime to build a car from scratch by yourself, if you had to do everything from harvesting the raw materials to filling it with refined, unleaded gasoline right before whipping it down to I-15. So an interesting other adhesive in this whole process sticking together is the trust that people have on each others’ goods and services, trusting that their work won’t be made obsolete by someone else’s incompetence (no matter how fancy the leather upholstery is on the seats, if the person accidentally ordered styrofoam instead of a cushion, then the whole thing is kind of ruined). It might be too much to expect the line worker to develop some sense of ownership in the product they’re helping to make since they’ll be paid every two weeks anyways. But it’s certainly the case that the manager can fire the person the first time they bring styrofoam and so the incentive will be to not mess up on the job, if you want to keep it.</p>

<h3 id="academy">Academy</h3>

<p>With respect to academy, I can also sooooort of get it. Kuhn argues in <em>The Structures of Scientific Revolution</em> on p. 19 that scientists have the comparative advantage of building off a paradigm without having to do any of the legwork of justifying or explaining the paradigm:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>The more rigid definition of the scientific group has other consequences. When the individual scientist can take a paradigm for granted, he need no longer, in his major works, attempt to build his field anew, starting from first principles and justifying the use of each concept introduced. That can be left to the writer of textbooks. Given a textbook, however, the creative scientist can begin his research where it leaves off and thus concentrate exclusively upon the subtlest and most esoteric aspects of the natural phenomena that concern his group.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>This takes a huge load off of scientists’ backs and they get to lean in to their comparative advantage and contribute the increased fruit from such devoted specialization to the economy, constitution of knowledge, whatever you want to call it. Textbook writers can specialize in translating this body of knowledge into whatever is accessible to the layperson, and others can specialize in making use of this knowledge.</p>

<p>So why am I feeling friction between this and my idea that a maverick thinker does need to understand something in terms of its atomic parts?</p>

<p>I think it’s because on first reading, you could interpret Kuhn as saying “scientists need to stick to the rigid paradigm, not questioning its axioms and first-principles and, in good foot soldier fashion, carry out their research duties” and that “textbook writers are the ones who distill research and hold any high-school educated person’s hand as they build from the ground up to make sense of it all”. I see value in doing both of these things, in doing primary research and reframing to deepen understanding.</p>

<p>I think of the videos I watch of academics at statistics conferences struggling to define a p-value, one of the building blocks of all statistics and the analysis it’s used to carry out in other fields. I think of Richard Feynman, a scientist’s scientist, and his devotion to making science clear for inexpert audiences. Didn’t he both win a Nobel and understand the science in simple terms? Maybe he’s hopelessly outnumbered by other laureates who exhibit no such need for pedagogical prowess in order to succeed in plundering paradigms.</p>

<p>So what question am I trying to answer here? I’m trying to answer whether one person could be expected to understand things all the way down, or whether there need to be scientists and textbook writers and policy makers and these people must be different. I’ve always envisioned philosopher-kings and intellectual-politicians; the practitioners of researched truths should themselves understand the researched truths, no? But I don’t think you can believe that the best scientist would be the best policy maker without taking some fundamental departure from specialization and comparative advantage. By the same reasoning, you couldn’t have the person best equipped to understand and thus disrupt climate science be the same person who is also best equipped to understand and thus disrupt political science and other sciences merely because that person understands math really well or is especially critical.</p>

<p>The idea that I find most scintillating now, at the end of writing this post, is that you can’t really compare the best of one field to the best of another field because they themselves are simply different paradigms, parametrizations of how a person sees the world, how they interpret data, what questions they ask, and so forth.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Partly motivated by my writing last night, where I take an interest in how maverick thinkers can actually buck against conventional wisdoms too unwieldy for a single person to have been responsible for them, I’m here tonight to meditate on how humans organize to do things that are too complicated for any individual human to do, such as the generation of a conventional wisdom.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Reasoning From First-Principles v. Inherited Wisdom</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2022/08/23/first-principles/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Reasoning From First-Principles v. Inherited Wisdom" /><published>2022-08-23T00:00:00-06:00</published><updated>2022-08-23T00:00:00-06:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2022/08/23/first-principles</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2022/08/23/first-principles/"><![CDATA[<p><img src="/assets/IMG_0555.jpg" alt="" /></p>
<ul>
  <li>I’ve been struck in recent years by a push–most availably from the Elon Musk genre of person–to reason from first principles. This on the one hand strikes me as good because I immediately can list off a litany of problems with reasoning from \(n\)th principles where \(n \neq 1\).</li>
  <li>Inherited conventional wisdom is hard to buck against because of availability biases and social pressures (how’s that for a conventional wisdom about conventional wisdoms?). But of course history is replete with examples of how conventional wisdom was wrong and it took some maverick thinker to unsheath our blinded eyes. Geoffrey Hinton said “The future depends on some graduate student who is deeply suspicious of everything I have said.”</li>
  <li>Reasoning by analogy is another example of relying on what you’ve learned about one situation to reason about another situation where this learned logic might not apply. So if you reason about what to do with your neighbor who annoys you with their loud music by analogizing “well what would you do if a mosquito was buzzing by your ear?”, we can probably all agree that you’ll want to find a different analogy.</li>
  <li>So we rely on the maverick thinker to understand arguments down to their first-principle constituent parts and to think through things as most appropriate for the situation, not ones that are in some dimension semantically similar and in some other crucial dimension categorically different (e.g., an annoying mosquito versus an annoying neighbor). This makes me think of a framework for making arguments for whom I’ve long harbored a crush.</li>
  <li>Think about if you decomposed arguments into their atomic bits, bits that could be understood by basically any high-school-educated English-speaker.</li>
  <li>Well, what if there were a framework where things were argued or explained in terms of other things? For example, you can argue that the world is 4.5 billion years old (and you probably do treat this as a perfectly unassailable fact). Okay, well, based on what?</li>
  <li>Well, based on the fact that radiometric dating shows the age of a rock based on breakdown of radioactive elements. Isotopes are variations of an element based on number of neutrons in nuclei. The isotopes of unstable radioactive elements–parent isotopes–turn into daughter isotopes in a predictable amount of time called a half-life.</li>
  <li>But how do we know about half-lives? And on and on and on until you get down to the level of atomicity such that the argument hinges not on isotopes but on “If you look really close, you can see the number of neurons.” at which point someone’s gonna go “ahhhh okay I get it” and it will feel like a solid argument to them.</li>
  <li>So I acknowledge that I like this because maverick thinkers seem to require understanding of first-principles and so if you could get more understanding, which I think tech is perfectly able to facilitate, since we’re no longer constrained to rigid forms of arguments but we can see arguments expanded and collapsed and animated dynamically as a person sees fit because of things like javascript and a browser instead of a printed book.</li>
  <li>And I also have to acknowledge that I think like this because I live in a democracy, and I want individuals to understand the decisions that they’re chipping in to make, and I don’t believe that right now they do.</li>
</ul>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[I’ve been struck in recent years by a push–most availably from the Elon Musk genre of person–to reason from first principles. This on the one hand strikes me as good because I immediately can list off a litany of problems with reasoning from \(n\)th principles where \(n \neq 1\). Inherited conventional wisdom is hard to buck against because of availability biases and social pressures (how’s that for a conventional wisdom about conventional wisdoms?). But of course history is replete with examples of how conventional wisdom was wrong and it took some maverick thinker to unsheath our blinded eyes. Geoffrey Hinton said “The future depends on some graduate student who is deeply suspicious of everything I have said.” Reasoning by analogy is another example of relying on what you’ve learned about one situation to reason about another situation where this learned logic might not apply. So if you reason about what to do with your neighbor who annoys you with their loud music by analogizing “well what would you do if a mosquito was buzzing by your ear?”, we can probably all agree that you’ll want to find a different analogy. So we rely on the maverick thinker to understand arguments down to their first-principle constituent parts and to think through things as most appropriate for the situation, not ones that are in some dimension semantically similar and in some other crucial dimension categorically different (e.g., an annoying mosquito versus an annoying neighbor). This makes me think of a framework for making arguments for whom I’ve long harbored a crush. Think about if you decomposed arguments into their atomic bits, bits that could be understood by basically any high-school-educated English-speaker. Well, what if there were a framework where things were argued or explained in terms of other things? For example, you can argue that the world is 4.5 billion years old (and you probably do treat this as a perfectly unassailable fact). Okay, well, based on what? Well, based on the fact that radiometric dating shows the age of a rock based on breakdown of radioactive elements. Isotopes are variations of an element based on number of neutrons in nuclei. The isotopes of unstable radioactive elements–parent isotopes–turn into daughter isotopes in a predictable amount of time called a half-life. But how do we know about half-lives? And on and on and on until you get down to the level of atomicity such that the argument hinges not on isotopes but on “If you look really close, you can see the number of neurons.” at which point someone’s gonna go “ahhhh okay I get it” and it will feel like a solid argument to them. So I acknowledge that I like this because maverick thinkers seem to require understanding of first-principles and so if you could get more understanding, which I think tech is perfectly able to facilitate, since we’re no longer constrained to rigid forms of arguments but we can see arguments expanded and collapsed and animated dynamically as a person sees fit because of things like javascript and a browser instead of a printed book. And I also have to acknowledge that I think like this because I live in a democracy, and I want individuals to understand the decisions that they’re chipping in to make, and I don’t believe that right now they do.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Philosophers v. Practical Persons</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2022/08/22/philosophers-v-practical/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Philosophers v. Practical Persons" /><published>2022-08-22T00:00:00-06:00</published><updated>2022-08-22T00:00:00-06:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2022/08/22/philosophers-v-practical</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2022/08/22/philosophers-v-practical/"><![CDATA[<p>I’ve got a buddy who rather likes rolling his eyes at economists; these were the deliverers of lectures that he’d rather not have had to sit through, who failed to make his college experience sufficiently practical or fun. To this friend, I feel the need to make an argument for “why science”?</p>

<p>On its face, the worthwhileness of science is almost tautological, if you see “science” as basically the accumulation of knowledge about how the world works, which can give you powers. Don’t you need to know that to make an AC unit (if you’re reading in summer) or a furnace (for winter), or to get water into the “running” camp (year round, I hope)? Those who see science as worth doing for these purposes I’ll call practical people.</p>

<p>For others, though, you don’t need science to be justified by what it allows you to <strong>do</strong>; it’s enough to allow you to <strong>understand</strong>. This genre of person I would call a philosopher, this definition more literally matching the root of the word than our running definition of “person who asks only questions that cannot be answered” (as this implies to me that this person kind of has <strong>philo</strong> less for <strong>soph</strong> than for questions, which strikes me as anything <strong>but</strong> <strong>soph</strong>). Learning about how the world works is intrinsically important for philosophers but for anyone who doesn’t care about the answer to a question (e.g., “how many blades of grass are there in the backyard?”), it needs to be instrumentally justified to be worth asking, let alone answering.</p>

<p>This is, I think, part of the issue that people of the Nicholas Nassim Taleb genre take with scientific endeavor. The issue taken here might extend to scientist’s taking their sweet time and druthers solving a question, regardless of its importance, since they don’t have “skin in the game”. Chomsky and his genre insist that scientific inquiry isn’t about external rewards, and what makes it work is the intrinsic motivation of the scientists which suffices as fuel for 80+ hour workweeks for relatively low wages, as seen in his MIT halls.</p>

<p>Another way that science runs out of usefulness is when it runs out of low-hanging fruit, an analogy for diminishing marginal returns and increasing marginal difficulty which I’ve heard Ross Douthat call one of Tyler Cowen’s favorite analogies. This might be the reason for what Peter Thiel laments as in “We were promised hovercars, and instead we got 140 characters.</p>

<p>So if one side wants to convince the other that pure discovery is worth the resources expended on it and the other one asks for hovercars, it seems that the only productive conversation can be had at the intersection of these two interests, where the scientists who love discovery obviously face a lower threshold of usefulness to find a discovery worth pursuing, and the practical people have a higher one, we can safely say that the latter is a subset of the former.</p>

<p>So the philosophers’ only hope is to convince the practical people that curiosity- or discovery-fueled science will yield better <strong>practical</strong> outcomes. How in the world would you do that?</p>

<p>I hope the answer is in <a href="https://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/full/10.1111/1475-5890.12195">this article by the innovation economist Nick Bloom</a>.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[I’ve got a buddy who rather likes rolling his eyes at economists; these were the deliverers of lectures that he’d rather not have had to sit through, who failed to make his college experience sufficiently practical or fun. To this friend, I feel the need to make an argument for “why science”?]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">A Local, Conflicted, Practical, English Conversation</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2018/08/22/hello-world/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="A Local, Conflicted, Practical, English Conversation" /><published>2018-08-22T00:00:00-06:00</published><updated>2018-08-22T00:00:00-06:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2018/08/22/hello-world</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2018/08/22/hello-world/"><![CDATA[<p><img src="/assets/IMG_0555.jpg" alt="" /></p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[]]></summary></entry></feed>